

Olivier Eeckhoutte

Freelance Solution Architect/ Tech Lead/ Senior Backend developer/ DevOps/ f-CTO

15+ years of professional experience Full Remote only

PROFILE

I feel lucky to work in a field I am very passionated about and evolves quickly.

Passionated about new technologies and very curious, I like to design and develop useful solutions and solve complex problems.

I enjoy learning new things all the time, be more and more proficient, discover raw gems and share my new discoveries with others.

I spent 3 years in the USA.

EDUCATION

Engineer of "Ecole Centrale de Lille", Graduated in 2011 Top Engineering School

Entrepreneurship and Management Specialities

Member of Iteem program: Second diploma delivered by the top Business school called Skema Business School

(Verification link: https://www.centraliens-lille.org/fr/addressbook/fullsearch/index)

CONTACT INFORMATIONS

+33 6 95 24 43 62

olivier.eeckhoutte@gmail.com Location: Morbihan, France

Professional Blog: https://leandeep.com (Articles

about my technical skills)

Linkedin: https://bit.ly/oeeckhout (Detailed profile)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Backend Developer, Breitling, Switzerland



Dec 2023 - Today

- Building from the ground up the new e-commerce platform leveraging an E-commerce Headless solution
- Development of event driven backend microservices (MACH Architecture using Python, GraphQL, AWS, Azure...)
- Pushing best practices (development, devops, tooling, practices) and proven working solutions from past experiences in an international team

f-CTO, PSIRIly project (in parallel of my main job at Breitling)

Sep 2024 - Today

- NDA signed so in short: Building a blockchain based crossplatform messaging app (mobile + web) for a family holding
- Technical stack: Rust + Flutter + Blockchain

Lead DevOps, TAG Heuer, Switzerland



Nov 2019 - Dev 2023 (4+ years)

- Developments of the cloud & python based middleware (custom Enterprise Service Bus) and API between the ecommerce website, Retail systems and lot's of internal backends systems

 More on this successful innovative platform here https://bit.ly/3gs0EHY and here https://bit.ly/3C0hX9W
- Developments of the custom made CIAM (Customer IAM) built on top of Keyclaok using python + LDAP migration + Keycloak plugin development
- Contributed to a new Ecom headless platform and other Web based platforms
- Managed different Azure/Kubernetes cluster builds & migrations

KEY SKILLS

Architecture

Clean Architecture, CQRS, Serverless,
Micro Services, MACH, API Gateway,
Service Mesh, SOA, Message Oriented
Architecture with topics and queues
(Kafka, Azure Service Bus, RabbitMQ...)
SQL (MySQL, Postgres), NoSQL
(MongoDB, Redis, CouchBase,
ElasticSearch, Influx, DynamoDB...)
SSO (keycloak), Oauth2, OIDC, Vault,
UML, IoT, Enterprise Workflows
(Camunda), REST, GraphQL

Data Science

Python, BigQuery, Machine Learning (scikit-learn, Pandas, TensorFlow/ Keras, Neural networks, FastAl, PyTorch), RPA, Scaping, Chatbots, AWS Al tools, Kubeflow, Prefect, Airflow, Dagster

DevOps/ Cloud

Azure, Amazon Web Services, GCP,
Docker, Monitoring, Tests Automation,
Linux (RedHat 7, CentOS, Debian),
Continuous Delivery, Software Factory
(Github, AWS CodePipeline, Gitlab,
CircleCl, Azure Devops, Bitbucket...),
Nginx, Kubernetes + custom dev
operators, OpenShift (v3.6 to v4), Hub &
Spoke Architecture, Terraform, 12
Factors

Blockchain

Nodes hosting, DeFi protocols,
Advanced backend Web3 development,
Solidity, Rust, Security, Hardhat, IPFS

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

- Setup all kind of different DevOps automations (Terraform, CI/ CD, Automated Tests, Monitoring...)
- Creation of an enterprise cross-channels Business Activity
 Monitoring (BAM) using a data stack (i.e. pandas, streamlit...)
- Tons of problems solved

Senior Backend Developer (in parallel of my main job at TAG Heuer)

Sept 2023 - Jan 2023 (customer: DLG Group, Switzerland)

 Marketing app (full backend realised from A to Z in Python and hosted in Google Cloud. I don't communicate on the details until it is officially launched)

Web3 trader/ Arbitrager/ Swing trader (in parallel of my main job)

Jul 2020 - Mar 2024 (customer: myself)

- Who better than yourself can take care of your finances?
- So I am building web3 arbitrage bots
- And I do Swing trading using technical analysis

Technical Leader, Engie Trading Center, Brussels CNGIC



Apr 2019 - Nov 19 (6 months)

- Create reusable and transversal tools for the developer teams
 (Data access management, automated end to end tests tools)
- Co-Technical Lead in an international team made of developers, data engineers & data analysts
- Migration OVH to AWS

DevOps, Adeo group, France



Feb 2018 - Apr 2019 (1+ year)

- Setup and Manage large Platform As A Service (300+ servers)
- Cloud Hybrid (On-Premise Google Cloud Platform)
- DevOps, Cloud Native Architecture
- Trainings animation (Kubernetes, Openshift, CI/CD Tools)
- Agile Methodology training and technical evangelisation
- SRE (Site Reliability Engineering): development, automation, monitoring (Python, Ansible, Terraform, Prometheus...)

KEY SKILLS

Web/ Mobile/ Backend dev

Javascript Single Page Apps (Svelte, AngularJS, Angular 2+, Ionic, Backbone...), Responsive Web Design, NodeJS, Webpack, HTML5 (WebRTC, WebSockets, Service Workers...), Cordova, iOS, Android, Java, TypeScript, Progressive Web Apps, TDD, BDD, DDD, Git, Python, Flutter

Project management/ Methods

Agile (Scrum, Kanban), Holacracy, Software Craftsmanship, Lean Management, Lean Startup, Design Thinking

Ecommerce

Salesforce.com, Salesforce Commerce Cloud, Saleor, Adyen, Paazl, SAP oData, Cegid, Forter, Riskified, Cegid, Akeneo (PIM), Bynder, GlobalE, Yext, OMS and other ecommerce related SAAS (Mailchimp, Twilio...)

Embedded dev/ Edge Computing

ESP32, Rust, Jetson Nano, k3s, balena, micropython, sensors, Raspberry Pi

Finance/ Administration

Web3 trading, Administration: I administrate my company since 2018

LANGUAGES

French English

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Technical Leader (& Data Champion), SwissLife



Mar 2015 - Feb 2018 (3 years)

- Technical Lead "Digital Solutions" (Design and development of the main customer portal)
- Transversal communities (Developers & DevOps) animator
- Dissemination of Agile & Software Craftsmanship + Continuous
 Delivery best practices
- Data Champion (Big Data /Machine Learning / Cloud migration contributor)
- Applicative Architecture Design
- Many innovation Studies and Proof Of Concept done
- Cognitive technologies referent
- Web & Mobile hybrid developments (Angular, Cordova, NodeJS)

Entrepreneurship (in parallel of my job at SwissLife)

Apr 2016 - Feb 2018

- Design and development of IoT object to open gates with face recognition
 - Automatic Tensorflow Models trainings engine manageable with Web/ Mobile interface
 - Deep Learning on Mobile devices and OTA updates
- Trainer in Project Management with Scrum, Lean Startup and Holacracy (School: ISCOM)
- Innovation Workshop Organiser (School: ISCOM)
- Startup Advisor (Technology stack): (Company: LaFinbox)
- AngularJS, NodeJS in Test Driven Development trainer

CTO, Geophyle, France

Mar 2014 - Mar 2015 (1 year)



- Team Management (7 developers)
- Architecture, Design and development of the solutions
- Projet Management (Budget / Planning / Ressources)
- Recruiting

TRAININGS & CERTIFICATIONS

2024 In progress: OSCP certification

2021 Learn how to integrate Django with Vue.js, MOOC

2021 Ethereum and Solidity Developer Bootcamp, MOOC

2020 The Complete 2020 Ethereum and Solidity

Developer Bootcamp, MOOC, Packtpub

2020 Learn to trade indexes, MOOC

2020 Forex trading with Ichimoku, MOOC

2019 Typescript fundamentals, MOOC

2019 Learning Blockchain Dev with EOS and C++, MOOC

2018 Google Cloud Platform introduction, Google, Lille

2017 Scalable Microservices with Kubernetes, Google,

Lille

2017 Running Container Clusters with Kubernetes, MOOC

2017 Lean Management Introduction, Advanced Path, SPOC, certif.

2017 Data Science, Advanced level, OCTO, Paris

2016 Introduction to statistics with R, MOOC

2016 Data Science foundations, OCTO, Paris

2016 Apache Spark essentials, MOOC

2016 Udacity, Georgia Tech, Kaggle, NanoDegree

Program: 420h of online training about Machine Learning

2016 AWS Solutions Architect Associate Certification

2016 Machine Learning, Stanford, Course Certificate,

MOOC

2016 Intermediate Python For Data Science, Datacamp

2016 Amazon Web Services for Data Science, MOOC

2016 Mastering Software Development, Arolla, Paris

2016 Holacracy, IGI Partners, Training + 4 month

mentoring

2016 Docker and Container Technologies, MOOC

2013 CEH v7 Training and Certification, Sysdream, Paris

2012 Energy Manager Professional Certification,

Schneider, Boston

HOBBIES

Creative/ Art - Security
 workshops - 3D Printing
 Beerology - Walking in Nature
 Travels - Water Sports
 Investing - Coding

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Application Architect Web & Mobile Technologies, Schneider-Electric France



Mar 2013 - Mar 2014 (1 year)

- Startup Creation Intrapreneurship project
- Facility Management Cross-Platforms Application (https://youtu.be/gl9t-XTco18)
- Architecture & Development lead (AWS, Web, Mobile, NoSQL)

Team Leader, Schneider-Electric USA, Boston

Schneider Blectric

Mar 2011 - Mar 2013 (2 years)

- Mobile Cross-Platforms architectures design & development
- Technical advisor in the strategy & Innovation department
- Mobile development Companies buyout auditor

Web/Mobile Developer, Schneider-Electric USA, Alameda



Jul 2009 - Mar 2011 (2.5 years)

- Web apps and mobile apps development
- Mobile Cross-Platforms development (SPA in JavaScript)

OTHER EXPERIENCES

Internships

- Developer, Arc International (2 months internship 2008)
- Salesman, Leroy Merlin plumbing shelf (3 months internship 2007)

Others

- At home computers repair (from 2005 to 2008)
- Big Data & Machine Learnin Meetup Organizer, Lille, 2018
- Public speaking (i.e: Nutigo, Big Data & Machine Learning, YO'Meet, during lot's Hackathons...)

RECOMMANDATIONS
ON DEMAND